this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program hello everybody
welcome to su radio in this episode we
have something about test-driven
development and interview by Johannes
link with lassika Scala Johannes has
considered joining the SU radio team and
the episode you hear today is his
prototype interview however he has
decided to not join the SU radio team
because he noticed that it's more worked
and he has time for in his current
situation we still decided to publish
his interview because we think it's a
good content and also offer obviously to
be fair towards la se the audio quality
is not quite up to our usual standards
but I think that the content is is
certainly good enough to even publish it
although the quality of the of the
recalling isn't isn't that great and so
if you you know if you don't like the
audio quality you don't have to post
that to the forums we know ok so thanks
again to Johannes for recording this
interview and also of course thanks to
Lhasa for for participating in and
providing the backbone of the content ok
that's it
have fun welcome listeners to a new
episode of software engineering radio my
name is Johanna think I am an
independent software coach living in
Germany and I'll be your host today I'm
very happy to have the CICC cascada as
my guest
welcome nothing thanks for this is my
first show for se radio so I'm feeling
pretty nervous um what about you well
it's my first first time being an
interview Garrus well so we're both
nervous I guess the topic of this
interview is test-driven development
although also known as some test-driven
design or test-first development or test
first programming more shortened TDD and
test REM development was mentioned a few
times in previous episodes but um has
never been covered in any detail before
we dive into the intricacies of TDD I
like you la say to tell us a bit about
you as a person mentum your professional
life right oh I'm I'm a geek or geek to
the bone so I've been working in the
industry for for a paycheck for around a
decade and basically doing most of that
doing programming so that that's my
background for the past four five years
I've been almost exclusively exclusively
working with agile methods I'm doing a
bit of coaching both for teams and
organizations but I've never really
stopped programming so I've done a lot
of hands-on pair programming for example
and so forth so you're still spending
most of your time frame yes actually
this in the beginning of the year I made
a decision to join a team for a longer
duration so that's something I've been
talking about for god knows how long and
now I decided to do it actual so I've
been I've been a project team member for
what seven months now okay and that
feels good better than being just a code
oh yes I think I think it's it was about
time so for the past five years before
this disengagement I had been working on
the same codebase continuously for the
maximum of two weeks and then I'd go
somewhere else
I maybe come back but still it's not the
same thing so I was starting to miss the
the frequent small wins and going live
getting a defect from production and so
forth and if it's good getting defects
from
I get to that later um you the reason I
invited you is that you published a book
I guess it was in 2008 or later
essentially 2007 2007 yeah and it's a
book about test rim development the
title of which is or test test ribbon
being well driven by something comes
with this right um connotation of being
addicted so do you consider yourself
being a kind of test junkie to some
degree yes so it definitely feels
awkward to work without tests so in that
sense yeah I guess you could call me a
test junkie so do you do that from time
to time I'm working without EFT what I'm
afraid I find myself in that situation
every now and then so for example
there's there's a legacy code base at
work where I'm working right now and
there's a lot of places that don't have
a sufficient coverage with tests also
there's a some technologies involved
that make it really hard to write tests
but and it feels feels weird
so definitely much better a much more
enjoyable and confident feeling when you
to go up with tests um TDD has been
around for a while and um still
different people mean different things
when they used the term how would you
define test-driven development
well I've had some discussions with
tinkling about this so technically the I
believe the first time tester and
development was defined in published
writing it did refer to mostly test
first programming combined with the idea
of of the tests and the minimum the
simplest thing that would possible work
kind of implementation and the next test
the implementation tests that that kind
of back-and-forth driving the design so
don't think about the the test-driven
development cycle yes
what so the ability the original
definition is was I can't remember where
it was but the first descriptions of TDD
were a combination of you first write
the test and then the implementation and
F an emphasis on emergent design so that
your design evolves strongly influenced
by the tests that you write and I think
personally I I have a less strict
definition of opportunity in my mind so
I I'm I'm mostly when I say TDD what I'm
really thinking about this
kind of a lightweight version of that so
test first definitely but you know you
do think about the design before you
start and you do have an idea of where
you want to drive your codebase but you
still let the co tell you that well this
doesn't feel right maybe we should go
into a different direction so there are
definitely different definitions and
that that's more or less mine so what
are the components of test-driven
development you already mentioned
writing the test first and letting the
code tell you where to go afterwards so
I imagine something like doing
refactoring after the test or during the
test yes so basically the the TDD cycle
being test code refactor those could
definitely be components so though
that's that's something you do all the
time when you do test-driven development
is there more to test-driven development
yet that you think is absolutely
necessary then I think there is yes so
for example if you if you look into the
the various studies there's numerous
studies research papers about the
effectiveness of TDD the influences on
quality called code quality and so forth
and when when you look at the the
studies that suggest that there there
might actually be a negative impact on
quality when it used TDD when you look
look into the the actual results what
they find is that certain
object-oriented metrics are they're
gonna a lower score and those but it's
not actually due to tester and
development as a method it's due to a
lack of lack of object-oriented design
skills
so basically TDD is a vehicle that gives
you a very natural rhythm to do good
object design the problem is that it
doesn't magically give you the sense of
what is good object-oriented design I
think that that is a kind of the missing
or the unmentioned component of TDD so
you don't think that TDD makes a good
program out of a bad one that does it
work the other way around so that um I
have heard people say that doing TDD
would distract developers from really
looking at the design and so being
sloppy about it
um yeah I've heard similar remarks and
right now and then I don't see that way
though I I kind of get the the idea of a
new workflow surf causing a disruption
in your in your current way of working
and there's there's definitely a
learning curve when you start doing
something as drastically different as
you have done before but I do I do think
that it it actually helps you helps you
improve it's just a different
perspective a different point of view
into looking at what you're doing and
looking at their design they're
basically using your test essay designs
for will like to get back to that how
tests can improve design I first go to
one of these basic things you said that
the first step in the TDD cycle is I'm
writing a test so it's obviously it will
be a test about something that doesn't
work yet how can you write write how can
you test something that doesn't work or
even exist yet well that's because we're
in TDD we're using the word test we're
kind of overloading the mainland so when
we when we write a test in as part of
the TDD cycle of test code refactor
they're not actually very fine anything
we're expressing a desire we're
expressing something that's missing the
kind of from talking more in the domain
of specification rather than
verification right so we're we're simply
pointing out something that's wrong or
missing from the current implementation
missing in terms of the user
requirements and depending depending a
bit on your code base or sometimes
sometimes it might be something fairly
low level of technical after
we are working with objects pieces of
code and every now and then the piece of
code that you're working on might
actually be very close to the that the
users domain so it depends so would you
say that most of the time the test I
write could be translated to you user
requirement or the other way around user
requirement could be translated into
such a test or is it the rare occasion
that I am working on the outside of my
system oh well your mileage may be right
but personally I tend to be working
below the the user requirement level and
to some degree it is due to the kind of
systems that I work on the kind of code
base that I can inherit from someone
else so but that that's what I tend to
tend to see around I also know of
several people who mostly work on higher
level tests and they they basically work
outside in all the time or at least most
of the time and for me it's kind of kind
of the opposite so most of the time I
work inside and try to grow things
towards something that's big enough to -
I actually mean something to the
end-users and then every now and then I
have the luxury of working on something
outside in specifying things from the
from the system perspective when you say
next three is that the better way well
for me it is at least simply because for
me it's so rare but it's hard to say if
I do it all the time I'd probably be
doing it maybe
too much every now so basically I
believe that there did there's somewhere
in the middle there's the the
theoretical optimum and it's not
actually that important where it is and
what it is it's good enough data that we
sort of find our way towards that that
optimal wherever it is rather than
diverge from it you mentioned the
learning curve so um obviously you were
a beginner once and there must have been
a time when you got hooked into DD and I
said oh yes now I feel or I can see that
it gives me value do you still remember
that time um I have wake remember wake
memories from that time oh I do you
remember this fuzzy err elf of my career
when I over time I went from basically
breaking the system and hacking it
hacking it until it works again and then
breaking it again and making another
step hoping that I actually get to fix
it
rather than reverse my changes and going
from that into much more steps where I
actually don't break the system for a
long time and completely shattered but
rather point out what's missing with
tests covering my back and implementing
that making sure that all tests pass
again
that somewhere in that transformation I
got hooked and basically nowadays it
feels weird if I don't have the test
covering my back so has some your work
experience changed fundamentally since
this point in time when you got hoped it
has definitely I I've stopped I've
stopped stressing that much
so basically when for example when we go
alive the protein I'm working on right
now we we deploy every two weeks I don't
really have any stress about I hope
there's no defects and so forth
it said the defects that we get they're
so rare and they're so non-critical then
it's actually a lot less stressed these
days compared to say eight years ago
when you say you have so few defects can
you tell us something about the numbers
oh I wouldn't know so the system are
working on it's it's existed for years
I've only been there for seven months
and there they have all kinds of systems
for different kinds of tickets and most
of them are really irrelevant and so far
I have no idea how many there are but
basically the
basically when when we start a new
two-week development iteration we we
don't have no we don't have massive
amount of defects and a couple of new
features we basically have mostly new
features and maybe at one or two bucks
dicks
um I guess I didn't catch you using the
word unit test you you said test you
said specification that very often
people used the word unit testing and
test-driven development as a sort of
synonym and what do you think is it the
same always just doing unit tests
something completely different than
doing TDD I don't I don't like the term
unit test that much I tip I do use it
every now and then but it it has say has
this problem that when you go to an
organization the word unit test has or
may have a completely different meaning
there compared to yours or another
companies so first of all unit
what's a unit well our technology is
this and we don't have objects so we
don't have classes what's our unit well
it's a source code source file for
example and that they have this
completely different taxonomy and unit
test me something and then in a
different company they're their unit
tests are obviously very micro level
very small they deal with one or two
objects at a time and so forth so first
of all there's there's this problem with
terminology second I I don't think that
I think it's somewhat arbitrary to say
that you should test drive with certain
types of tests
so even though most of the tests that I
write when I do TDD are or are such that
you could call them unit tests
meaning they they on a very fine
granularity just testing a single method
or object yes
so most of the time that the test that I
wrap it involves a couple of objects no
no side effects if there are side
effects I make sure that I clean that up
so that the next for the next test it's
clean plate again but most of the time
it's it's a couple of objects doing
something very very small specific very
isolated but every now and then I do
write other kinds of tests for example I
might set up a a small cluster of
graphical components basically create a
small a tiny tiny application where this
cup of gooey components are they both
exist there and they interact and that's
no that's no longer a unit test
according to the stricter definitions
but I think it still makes sense to test
right that particular thing and in that
situation that approach might be the
best so you would really go to the
graphical user interface and test that
that's well preferably not the dhole
interface but small portions of it so
you might take you might have a button
in a text field and they they have some
kind of interaction that you want them
to have so you might just pop up with a
small tiny window though that has just
one button and just one text field
nothing else but basically that's
already you're already bringing in
plumbing in in the form of the the
graphical user interface framework swing
or something else so that's already a
bit too much infrastructure to be called
unit tests
but the doing distance on your
definition for doing some tests on that
level I it guess you'd require other
tools than just a plain chair unit and
unit or whatever to
able to all will to click buttons stuff
like that yeah yeah if you do that a lot
and I think you should at least consider
using some kind of frameworks or pay
very very close attention that they're
not creating a maintenance nightmare for
yourself basically refactoring various
code extracting these bit differently
similar things we're basically starting
to build up your own test harness for
that kind of code
but you don't need special tools like
capturing play technology well I've
heard yeah that capture replay that's
it's it's a nice idea the problem is
that you don't have something to record
so if you're missing a button somewhere
how do you record that when you click a
button
something happens you don't have a
button that's a fair point yeah
I hear people talk about using TDD in
all kinds of areas like java.net Python
Ruby you name it
have you hit upon technologies that do
not lend themselves well to test-driven
development where you can't do it at all
um well certainly some technologies make
it a lot more difficult to write tests
um for example last year I went to I was
in Bangalore India and I was there for
visiting a Java team but they right in
the next room there was this this group
of people working on C code we we kind
of agreed that I go and see if I could
helped him um it was interesting another
C programmer by any means so I don't
really I don't have the indanone about
there are all kinds of things that you
can do and so forth but we we did look
at it and make some progress the the
thing is that the language the language
makes you really work hard for for
getting those tests Creed's you can you
can do it definitely but it's it's a lot
more verbose and to say the API is
available the testing frameworks there
are much much lower level than your
regular chair unit them or and unit and
so forth thanks for one side of it there
there's also the other side that which
is actually very interesting um when
when you work with languages that need
compilation like with the C guys well
when I when I work on Java in a modern
ID such as Eclipse I basically just I
type a type and a type and then I run
tests I don't compile is the IDE does
that continuously so it's it's so
instantaneous that I you don't have to
think about it but when you work with
see for example compilation is actually
a big thing so when you want to run the
tests you have to stop you have to
compile
takes a while it might take a couple of
seconds but it might take ten seconds
and then then you run the test so the
feedback cycle come becomes it's not no
longer one second it might be ten
seconds and that actually fundamentally
changes the way you you run your through
your TDD cycle well my friend passivity
calls this kind of memory the exact term
but basically he is talking about this
Oh optimistic locking type of TDD where
you when you stop to think about
something you basically you just you
save and you start compiling and running
the tests and then you should continue
typing again immediately so that
basically in the background the compiler
is compiling and when the compiler is
done you run the tests but you are
already moved on so you are already
continuing with the expectation that the
test will fail or will pass in a certain
way so you you assume that your
assumptions and understanding of the
code is correct and most of the time
this might work but every now and then
turns out that the test didn't fail it
was supposed to fail or hey the testing
impasse it was supposed to pass so you
you made any false assumption somewhere
and you have to basically rewind here's
your mind and whatever it caught you've
already written after the last test
basically so you have to go back and
stop again think about what's going on
here so it's a bit you can do it but
it's it looks differently feels
different
so do you think in TDD in those
environment is still worth it where's
the border how long can the feedback
cycle take that it's still worth doing
TDD
Oh 42 I had annoyed okay yeah I'd say
that I haven't seen an environment where
where I wouldn't consider TDD being
beneficial part least potentially
beneficial because after all it's up to
the individual yeah personally I haven't
seen an environment where I wouldn't do
TDD
have you ever worked in a C++
environment with big systems that take
like maybe 15 minutes to build even
longer personally all I talked with some
people for example in this very
interesting situation where a London
bank they're working on C++ and
basically their toolset is something
like VI or Emacs they don't have
built-in refactorings in their fancy IDs
there are no IDs all their tears we
shall studio so they still lead TDD and
for example refactoring they did by
writing shell scripts that mangle your
source source code your source files
with regular expressions tools like said
and Bach and that sounded very very
laborious but what they decided to do so
obviously they and they continue doing
it so obviously they saw the value even
though they they were working on a big
cyst and with difficult technology and
C++ it's not not the friendliest the
programmer friendliest language and hey
yeah but personally I haven't seen that
but I've heard a lot of people say that
it can be done even though it sounds
awful we actually do it we're happy what
I see are two sites the one side ism is
it worth doing that from objective view
like if you count the number of defects
in the time you save not working on
those defects because you they didn't
get into the production system in the
first place and the other side how does
it feel to people so um what length of
our feedback cycle to normal developers
get up with so that they still bear this
heavy load of going
psycho was iets it's very hard to say
now let's get back to some of the more
technical things like you you mentioned
that you sometimes go away from the
strict unit testing and test testing an
isolation thing but when you want to do
that and you have things like file
systems databases and stuff like that
you probably have to decouple you the
object you want to test or the unit you
want to test from other things from
infrastructure from databases and stuff
like that how do you go about that oh
well one of the one of the big core
techniques there is basically dependency
injection so you so you basically avoid
using the word new if you're working in
Java so you don't you want to de couple
the decouple the code under test or the
code that you run want to test you want
to decouple that from the implementation
of its collaborators so for example
rather than in your constructor saying
this dot foo equals new widget you
basically
pass that reagent that you mean the
dependency from into your constructor
that kind of thing so basically in your
test you can then compost objects with
some of their dependencies faked out or
using mock objects something like this I
think that that's that's the the most
essential technique there he's it a
difficult technique I have heard used
the word mock object in so many
different ways that sometimes confuses
me
oh well I don't find it that that
difficult now I'm curious about the
confusion about mock objects yeah
sometimes people talk about mock mock
objects and just means an object
implementing an interface that just
returns predefined values why sometimes
they're using something like easy mark
to have them a seemingly complicated way
to define the behavior of this mock
object and during the test time so them
obviously some different kinds of mock
objects all right there's a there's a
couple of taxonomy in play here I think
one of them is it's basically written by
Martin Fowler so he some years ago he
brought this this particle called mocks
art stops nothing you might want to
check the title but I will be here till
it's shown it right so he he provides
this classification which i think is
very fairly global that there there are
stops makes and mocks where stops would
be the the most simple implementation of
an interface you can think of where they
the methods basically they either do
nothing or they return a a fixed value
by mal or a zero or fifteen now
something basically hard-code everything
then there's there are fakes which are
more like a lightweight alternative
implementation for the real thing so
basically when you take a fake object
and you poke it it acts like the real
thing but it's not the real saving then
as an example if I have a fake database
then it would really stall values store
columns something there
basically a fake database could be a
hashman now I see something implemented
on top of a hash map so you don't
actually persist anything as such to to
a disk and you rather keep keep those
all of those objects in memory and when
you do a lookup you might be trade
through all of the objects until you
find the right the one that you're
looking for something so in a way it's
simulating the real object yes you could
say that and then there's the third
category the mock objects which would be
more like configurable spies that you
can take and take a mock object for a
given interface and then you can tell to
behave behave like this when this
happens and for example you can tell
them to fail your test if this happens
that kind of things so that I think
that's a fairly global universally
accepted classification or taxonomy of
different kind of test doubles if you
want
just the testing framework of your
choice give you the capability to to
have those kind of mock objects or do I
need other tools putting there now
depending on your technology of course
all personally I'll mostly work with
Java and for the past couple years I've
increasingly been using this tool called
che Dave so Jay Davis you say it is a
testing framework of one kind and it
integrates JMO so it gives you a built
in facility for creating more contacts
and it happens to use J mock underneath
but there's a there's a host of other
other equally good for any answer doing
that so usually I need another friend
basically yes you can write more
projects by hand for example but it does
get tedious so yes you do want to use a
framework sorry for a library yes I
understand that and I can mock out or
fake out objects dependencies when I do
not want to test those but at one time
or another I will have to need to use a
real database or the real file system or
calling the web servers how can I test
drive those well one example of a
situation you want you do that would be
for example of data access object so but
let's say you're working on an
application that that's sitting on top
of a relational database and you have
these data access objects that that are
responsible for moving data from the
database and turning them into objects
that you can manipulate and work with or
they might take in a domain object then
make sure that mean it gets persisted
into the database so how do you test
write those well you know you there's a
couple of ways for example in Java you
could you can mark or fake the JDBC
interfaces if you happen to use that
that API or you could actually launch a
an actual relational database and run
your test against that database and
there I think I think that's an example
where I by default maybe go with the
database
but you're not thinking about this whole
thing um all right cool which takes half
a minute and then opening a couple of
sessions which takes another ten in the
seconds for every session oh yeah so
that's that's where I'd actually go for
the lightweight implementation looks
like h2 or hsql so there are there are a
bunch of in-memory databases that are
really lightweight and they take a
fraction of a second to launch so
basically using a lightweight database
that you might call it a fake but it's
it's it's an actually it's a decent drop
their database says no Oracle or moisted
so when I work with for example if you
work with hibernate not sure if you're
familiar with it but it has this its own
query language and I'm definitely not a
hibernate bore and I have trouble
remembering how to do this and how to do
left outer joins in with hibernates
query language
so if I if I pick everything
I really I don't have I can write a test
I can write a test that says when I do
this to you will mr. data object or data
access object then you should make this
kind of an API call to describe in it
interface that I've marked but I have no
idea whether that that API call the the
syntax of the query statement whether
that's correct or not so I'd rather work
against the real database so that I can
actually write meaningful tests that
tell me something
so so what I take from that is that
whenever you using mock objects to to
step out stuff you really have to know
this stuff quite well at least the API
and how it's going to be used otherwise
you can't write the correct mock object
for it example another another example
of against of Technology domain where I
I find myself doing kind of a similar
compromise if you will basically not
using extremely isolated have pure micro
tests
so what about the costs of doing
test-driven development is it more
expensive to develop in a test first
style than to program without automated
tests I guess most people would argue
that it is at least in the beginning um
well there's definitely a cost of the
learning curve so you do have the
initial dip in productivity enough and
then there's there's a bunch of studies
research that attempts to prove or
measure some kind of a difference
between test lasts and test first or
test first and test never and the
problem there is that it's never really
a solid proof because you you'd really
have to take the same persons or the
same people and have let them work on
something with one technique for a while
and then this we brainwash them and make
them forget everything they they learned
and found out during that time and then
have them redo it
the same thing with the different
technique to get get a meaningful
comparison so there's a bunch of
research that that suggests this and or
suggest the other
but basically it's I find that it's down
to our subjective opinion really whether
it it is more costly or less costly and
so forth and personally I have known no
doubt that it is more productive for me
to do tests first than test last what
about the teams you have seen is your
impression that they are getting faster
with time faster than they were before
you started introducing test-driven
development
well I'd say that they tend to get
faster again that the problem there is
that TDD is not the only force in play
so that also overtime you grow your
codebase you might grow your team size
suddenly you have to you started with
one team of five people now you have two
teams of five people you or you might
have ten teams so over time all kinds of
other variables change so it's really
hard to say on whether they've actually
gone faster or not because the overall
output doesn't directly relate to the
productivity of an individual but
there's a lot of variables in play well
again as subjectively in my opinion the
teams that adopt TDD they they do get
faster compared to what I assumed I
imagined that they would be if they
hadn't adopted TDD a lot of it is due to
having tests so I think I think that the
biggest difference comes from simply
having enough unit tests to get to give
you this comfortable safety net and on
top of that there there are some
benefits from from improved code quality
improved design and of course other
things like people learn you know
yeah some argue that having too many
tests will slow you down because team
you not only have to change the code and
the production code but also know the
test code right yeah I've heard that a
lot well I think that's that's perhaps a
second major sort of unmentioned core of
of TDD so it's not enough to just go
through the sabbatical of tests or
refactor you also have to have some kind
of an a vision some kind of sense for
object time and you have to refactor
your test code as well it's not just
refactor
production code you have to be as
merciless towards your test code do you
think the same design guidelines
principles hold for test codes as for
production code I believe they do but
again principles or principles not rules
so for example you might have different
principles suggest opposite directions
and basically you have to you have to
make a subjective decision that okay so
this this year there's a bit of
duplication there but it having this bit
of duplication it gives me a slight
slightly better understandable test for
example so you might decide to leave
that bit of duplication there even
though certain principles suggest that
you should get rid of it and you
wouldn't find the situation in
production code well you might but but
it's a it's a slightly different world
so it in production code but you you
tend to do you tend to have less less of
this like data-driven type of blocks of
code whereas in the test code when
you're basically
describing scenarios not the domain such
so you're describing scenarios which are
inherently that bit different nature
than that the problem domain that
they're trying to model with your
production
so I think there is there is a
difference it might be subtle but I
think there is a slight difference let's
go to to something
not completely different but different
you in your book you differentiate
between tester and development and
acceptance test-driven development and
you told me that you're also doing a bit
of behavior driven development what's
the difference between those three award
it's one just the evolution of the other
how how could we how could we pick those
three things right
so I'll pick on the behavior driven
development first and the the origins of
BDD or behavioral development are are
very close to TDD the the turbidity was
coined by Dan North and according to Dan
he he adopted this this new vocabulary
where you don't talk about test but
specifications of behaviors
in order to better team each tester and
development so well I mentioned earlier
that we saw sort of overloaded the
meaning of the word tempest also we're a
lot of people have this built-in idea of
test testing meaning verification after
the fact and in TDD we're talking about
this upfront specification of what
doesn't exist yet so there is a mismatch
and what Dan wanted to accomplish
originally with what he then called BDD
was a different vocabulary that better
suits the mindset of of tester and vom
so that's that's where BDD started but
it'd be impossible to kind of two
directions now one is TDD evolution into
basically developer tips very micro
level but expressed in with the slightly
different vocabulary so where you you
want to express your tests not as tests
but well specifications so TDD done
right
basically TDD done right and the other
the other direction is then actually a
aesthetics course acceptance test your
development so point going away from the
low level like unit test type of
tests or even specifications and trying
to try to go outside in so that you you
express things from the users
perspective and you start getting more
into the the domain of the end user the
user interface the ubiquitous language
of the users not the programmers
so then you natural there's a link to
our story testing or acceptance testing
and then it that that's I think the two
major directions that BDD has evolved so
so what do you think that BDD makes TDD
and acceptance TDD redundant oh that
doesn't sound right
I want to say that I'd say that
BDD means these two different form
groups they're they're just variations
of of TDD or acceptance test or indigo
but be as I understand you BDD can cover
both camps well yes so the term the term
again it's a bit overloaded so that you
have different kinds of BDD you have the
the code oriented behavior of different
developments and you have the feature or
functionality oriented BDD now but
probably you're using different tools
for for these different ends of BDD the
BDD spectrum so in practice you are
actually doing two different things even
though both of them might be called BDD
depending on who you talk to
mm-hmm do you have any preference in
tools oh well for well I mentioned Jay
Dave earlier and I call it a testing
framework yeah it's actually a behavior
current development framework so that it
invests these that these concepts of the
behavior driven development its
vocabulary it's basically it's
inspiration has been r-spec what you say
it will be based tool and actually
r-spec or nowadays cucumber twosome and
if an offspring from the r-spec project
well cucumber would be my it's kind of
my favorite tool for the acceptance type
of BDD
so when you're in in projects do you
still consider to use what's the goal
like is the acceptance testing tools
like Fitness Wow well but I haven't
worked with Fitness for extended periods
of time so I bumped into it several
times all written some pictures and so
forth and I found it to be a reasonably
good tool and but they're there I think
there's there's a big enough difference
with the kind of tabular table based or
even the narrative more narrative
variations of Fitness pictures for
example and with the kind of test ID or
scenarios they can describe with tools
like cucumber so the differences is not
huge but it's big enough that I I don't
really consider tools like Fitness
anymore well of course if there's a if
there is a legacy there's some existing
base of fitness tests then I probably
end up continuing on that path at least
to start with but given a clean plate
I'd probably go for cucumber or
something like that you told me that you
are about to write another book
yeah well it's actually uh it's about
unit testing so my publisher Manning
publications they asked me if I'd if I'd
like to work with royal sugar on a Roy
wrote a book called the RF part of unit
testing and it's a dotnet book so Roy's
done that guy and I'm a travel guys so
on this this collaboration is is going
to become some some kind of a a
translation
fuel of a boys book into the Java world
so obviously some of the concepts are
different and do not apply as well be a
it won't be a direct translations
translation of course but something like
that so that it's going beyond the flame
test-driven stuff yeah well we will
mention TBD and give a short
introduction but or basically did focus
there is on on the art of writing tests
or specifications if you use the BDD
vocabulary some I'm the really geek
mammal word for word yes it's gonna be a
geek book a lot of code a hundred or so
called ulis things also so it won't be
spent in your grandmother rates when
it's going to be at well it's hard to
say I haven't really started yet but
it's not this year that that I can say
for sure but we'll see a year for more I
hope to have it in my hands okay you
notes mmm pretty ambitious um before we
wrap up is there anything else you would
like to add well that's it that's a
tough one well oh oh you caught me by
surprise there oh nothing comes to mind
nothing comes to myself I actually have
a question on my mind last time I met
you there was a tan HL 2008 and runt and
you were one of the stars in proclaiming
of the stars which is basically a
competition of pairs doing test-driven
development in public yeah and you won
the competition actually how did you do
that and we well we pride our show the
penalty chances aside from that
technologies that were kind of
interesting to the audience
I guess we do entertain people it's
really hard to say okay
Thank You NASA for taking the time to
answer my questions at length and in
great detail it's been a great passion
there's no hope to see you soon and bye
bye bye thanks for listening to software
engineering radio software engineer
radio is an educational program brought
to you by hillside Europe if you want
more information about the podcast and
all the other episodes visit our website
at se - radio dotnet if you want to
support us you can donate to the SU
radio team by our website or you can
advertise for se radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and the slash dot button to
contact the team please send email to
team at SC - radio net or it is specific
to an episode please use the comments
facility on the website so other people
can react to your comments this episode
of se radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under the creative
comments 2.5 license please see the
website for details thanks to Charlie
Crowell and the pot site Music Network
for the music used in this show the song
is called Vegas Achtung